Alejandro Parga-Becerra MD PhD

alejandro-parga.github.io

Neuroscientist

apargab@gmail.com

+1(480)244-5947

SUMMARY

As a neuroscientist with medical training and advanced research skills in **neuro-electrophysiology**, I am an expert on the **synaptic plasticity** of neuronal circuits and their alterations in functional brain disorders. In my research, I bring together electrophysiological tools to investigate the function of neuronal networks. My strengths are in the **interpretation of neuro-anatomical studies** and the **biophysics** involved in hippocampal neuronal circuits. My goal is to understand the function of neuronal ensembles that is relevant to cognitive function and translate this knowledge into concrete applications that potentiate technology to modulate neuronal networks.

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

2017-present

Advanced electrophysiological training

Research Scientist/Engineer3 – Department of Physiology and Biophysics – UW, Seattle | Dembrow lab

- •Multimodal analysis of primate infragranular pyramidal neurons and their modulation Senior Fellow - Department of Neurology - University of Washington, Seattle Epilepsy Center of Excellence and Neurology Service VA Puget Sound | Ransom lab
- Regulation of Extra-synaptic GABA_A Receptors in Health and Disease.¹

2015-2016 *Electrophysiological tools, Optogenetics, and Computational training Postdoctoral Research Associate* - University of Arizona, Phoenix Campus | Anderson lab

- Optogenetic regulation of CSD using targeted pyramidal inhibition and activation.²
- Neurosteroid action on Cortical Spreading Depression (CSD) through differential GABAergic signal onto pyramidal neuron.

2008-2014

Pharmacological and Neuroanatomical training

Research Assistant – Barrow Neurological Institute - ASU, Phoenix | Hammer lab

- Retrograded trans-synaptic tracing of auditory neuronal circuits using pseudorables virus-152.
- Dopamine-induced auditory cortical activation and attenuation by D2-like receptorselective antagonist in the caudatoputamen of the rat.⁵

EDUCATION

2014

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) Neuroscience

Barrow Neurological Institute - ASU - Phoenix

Dissertation: Cortical auditory functional activation by cortico-striato-thalamo-cortico circuits: An endogenous mechanism of the brain to activate the auditory cortex, relevant to the neuronal basis of auditory hallucinations. https://repository.asu.edu/items/27433
2006

Postgraduate Medical Training

1.40064/2006

La Arandia Military Base - Caqueta - ML 18964/2006

EMS physician | Military Surgical Brigates | Tropical Diseases Service.

2005 Doctor of Medicine (MD) Neurophysiology

National University of Colombia - COM Bogota

Clerkship - San Rafael Hospital/Ramon Gonzalez Valencia University Hospital - UIS

REPRESENTATIVE PUBLICATIONS AND WORKS IN PROGRESS

RESEARCH SKILLS

in vitro and in vivo electrophysiology Tracing neuronal circuits with viral vectors Opto/chemogenetics Confocal and multiphoton microscopy Patch-Seq Intrinsic Optical Signal imaging Stereotaxic intracranial surgeries in situ hybridization immuno-histochemistry Fluorogold iontophoretic infusions for cellular labeling

COMPUTATIONAL SKILLS

Programming Languages

Python, C++

Version Control

GIT

Imaging

ImageJ

NiE

Imaging Workbench Stereoinvestigator

Neurolucida

Data Recording

Igor Pro, MIES, PolyScan2, pClamp, Linlab

Statistics

Origin, SPSS, SAS, STATA Blaise, CDISC

- 1. **A. Parga** & C. Ransom (2021). Traumatic brain injury broadly affects GABAergic signaling in dentate gyrus granule cells. *eNeuro*, 8 (3) 0055-20.2021 doi: 10.1523/ENEURO.0055-20.2021
- 2. **A. Parga** & T. Anderson (2017). Targeted optogenetic pyramidal neurons to regulate cortical spreading depression. *Journal of Neurophysiology*. in revision.
- 3. **A. Parga**, G. Muñoz & R. P. Hammer (2016) Excessive striatal dopamine activates the auditory cortex via striato-thalamo-cortical projections in the rat. *Biological Psychiatry* 77(9), 62S. doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.03.006
- 4. A. N. Hoffman, **A. Parga**, P. Paode, L. R. Watterson, E. M. Nikulina, R. P. Hammer, Jr., and C. D. Conrad (2015). Chronic stress-enhanced fear memories are associated with induced amygdala zif268 expression and are resistant to reconsolidation. *Neurobiology of Learning and Memory*, 120, 61-8. doi: 10.1016/j.nlm.2015.02.004.
- 5. **A. Parga** & R. P Hammer (2012). Auditory cortical activation after dopamine infusion in caudal caudatoputamen of the rat. *Biological Psychiatry*, 71(8), 312S. doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2012.02.014